Uh good morning. Welcome to
meditation. And
uh before we start, I'm going to show
you some pictures to remind you. We're
going to do a five houses
meditation. And here's
uh pictures, Francisco, some of the
pictures, but not all. So, here's the
first
one. And that's just to remind you of
what the five houses are. And the idea
is that we had a visit to Princeton
University a week ago or something and
we had some classes there and
uh in they have different houses and
different departments. Uh so the
university and is a big entity. It has I
don't know $30
billion
endowment and they take care the
university kind of takes care of all the
paperwork and all that and they keep the
place you know looking good which is
really really difficult because it's
it's huge and they build new buildings
all the time and things like that and
then u then there are
departments and when you go to the
university you specialize
you you get a PhD in a certain subject
and you join a department
uh although you can visit other
department to expand your
knowledge. So uh this is a place called
Holder
Tower and
uh uh it's it's close to my house. So I
was in Proctor House. Proctor House is
uh mainly for uh religion. So I was a
religion major and uh so each each
student makes a decision and by the way
you get a year or two to make the
decision. You don't make the decision
when you get there and uh you try
different things for the first year or
two and then you see what fits you like
a pair of pants and I I originally
started in the politics department uh
because it was the anti-war days and
then I didn't they were too crazy and
then I I went to
psychology and I'll never forget there
was a uh famous psychologist came to
talk and she had a cup of coffee and she
was going like this and then I was
looking at her and I
said I don't want to be a psychologist
you know and then my backup was religion
uh because I was really interested in
and I wanted to be a priest so um so
anyway that was my college but I did
change my major I think three times uh
and that's okay they encouraged that
because You are how old? You're 20 years
old. And to make a decision what you
want to do for your whole life at that
stupid age is not very wise, right? How
old are your kids? Your boys are older.
Yeah. So, they're not that stupid. But
um but uh anyway, uh you make your
decision for your house. I'm going to
review the houses and then we're going
to do a closed eye meditation about the
houses. Okay. Next one,
Francisco. Uh, so first house uh is
called classics house and uh I guess
pretty much that's how a ACI started.
You know, we started as ACI started as
uh the GES course uh shortened for
Westerners and for foreigners and uh and
it was a good job. I'm proud of that
guy. uh it's a good representation of
the Gishi course and so uh kind of this
guy and don't forget you can be a Tim
remind me you can be a member you can be
a lecturer
instructor teacher or a master okay
member instructor teacher and then a
master you so you work up by the way to
be a member
You don't you don't have to I mean it's
like joining a department at Princeton.
You don't know anything and you don't
have to know anything. You just have to
know you want to be in that department
and then then you start learning. Okay.
All right. So that's one option that you
have in ACI. That's the first house is
called classics
house. And then second
house is
called somebody house. And uh in the
original ACI in New York in the 90s we
did
uh we also did meditations and we had a
whole uh what do you call it curriculum
of different meditations and they are
good. If you don't know about them you
should review them. You should there are
recordings on the what do you call that
thing knowledge base. Yeah. So basically
uh this is this is for meditators. Uh
and I wanted to mention this morning
that uh medit this samadei house is a
good
example of a house which in my vision
uh would serve two purposes. You know,
one is spiritual and there would be
meditation classes and meditation
courses and
meditation skills where uh and
especially as a teacher where you are
doing uh Buddhist meditations uh and
then but I also would like to see and
it's something we're not very strong in.
I often see in the
press, you know, reports that Google has
hired two meditation teachers. And, you
know, I sometimes I look and see, I
wonder what they're teaching there. And
it's really weird stuff. And uh so I I
feel strange that uh we have such uh
authentic meditation. We have thousands
of years of good instruction on how to
meditate. And then we we've never been
able to
really create a program for secular
meditation or meditation by people. Uh
there are people I go on tours. I go on
DCI tours. I remember a long long time
ago I went to Europe and and I was
teaching a meditation class and somebody
said look I'm just never going to be a
Buddhist you know I'm not interested but
I would really like to learn to meditate
for my business or or for my personal
life and I I think each
house should have a
secular branch and and a spiritual
branch. So I see the houses split like a
pagod of five floors and then I see a
vertical split where uh there's a
spiritual samadei house courses and
teachers who specialize in that and then
there's a secular or non-religious uh
meditation courses and I think as a as a
group as an organization
uh we've missed an opportunity. I think
we we could have served more people if
we had that clear distinction
and and there is a thing where you know
in in corporate in in America in New
York for example uh you have to be very
careful not to be religious and it's a
legal requirement and it's a and it's
sort of a
cultural requirement. you're not allowed
to be religious in the company and it
and it's unfair to the people that you
hire who are not Buddhist. So uh I think
we should we should be able to have each
house should have specialists who can go
out to a corporation and they understand
corporations
uh or other kinds of organizations and
then there should be somebody masters
who are Buddhist and who can teach you
Buddhist meditations. So, so I see it as
two each
department should have two two
departments or two two subd departments.
Okay, next one. Francisco, what's this
called? Yeah, this is mountain house and
uh it's
retreat and uh what the the distinction
I applied the dichotomy I just applied
it very much applies to mountainhouse
also and I I believe
uh my my jewelry company was successful
because I did many many innovation trees
and I think uh it's a
wonderful opportunity to help
uh corporations,
businesses succeed and also to help the
mental health of the executives in the
corporations because they're under
tremendous stress and and uh if they
could learn to do retreat as a as a
businessman then that would be really
nice and and we again we failed in that.
We haven't really done that well. We
haven't really helped people this way.
There is some programs we've done, but
not as not as well as we could have. By
the way, the things we did do well are
are really
kickass. Okay. And those are good, but I
think we could do more. Okay, next
picture. What's it called? Staircase
house.
And uh basically this person has learned
the 14
uh years of lum by the way that's the
that's pretty much the most complete lum
rim you could ever do. There's there's
nothing more than
that. You could spread out horizontally
to other lum rims uh by sonapa or other
teachers there. There are but uh but
basically the structure of it is is the
most
detailed and uh and the by the way the
best written that book uh a gift of
liberation thrust into the palm of your
hands is
uh is probably the best Tibetan book
ever written. the the person who
transcribed it and the person who edited
it was
unbelievable beyond beyond anybody as a
writer and uh so anyway uh and he was my
teacher's teacher so uh anyway uh again
you'd have to think about
applications to secular life and and I
have this app uh inside timer. I use it
uh for the timer because I like it. I
like the bell. We'll do the bell. Okay.
Today, uh you have a choice of bells. Uh
I use it for the bell. And then there's
a lot there's many many uh meditations
offered uh on the on the app and uh it's
almost too many in uh and a lot of them
in my opinion are kind of silly but uh
but I think uh you
could you could have almost like a
psychological treatment of people with
lam rim which is not Buddhist you know
and but it would take some creativity.
It would take some you'd have to be a
good l room teacher to to use it for non
Buddhists. Okay. But it would be useful
and you see that on that app. You see
that kind of thing. It would take a it
would take a lot of thought but you
could do it. I think so. So that house
staircase house could have a
secular. Okay. Uh next one. Uh next
one's called Diamond House and uh you
know obviously those of you who know
about the Diamond Way courses of of ACI
uh the the
courses the Diamond Way course by the
way I had a note from Mr. been in
Vietnam uh maybe seven, eight years ago,
I remember. And he said,
um people are are people in some people
in Vietnam ask me why is Gishi Michael
doing D does he do diamond way? Because
it's not nice. It's not clean. It's
dirty. It's strange, you know. Um you
know, is it where did you get this from?
Where does this come from? you know, and
then I I wrote him back. I actually had
some fun. I
uh half of the books from ancient India,
half of the Buddhist books are diamond
ring. Exactly half, you know. So you're
talking
990 texts,
450ome are are 490 are are are diamond
way, you know, and the commentaries
there are over
2,000 and that's before it reached the
Himalayas, you know. So you know to say
is it Buddhism or not is a strange
question for us because we grew up with
I grew up with it and my teacher taught
it to me for 30 years. So there is a
diamond
way what do you call it
scholastic tradition in in a scriptural
tradition and it's very very deep and
it's very very wonderful and very clean
and very beautiful and uh you know but
the name tantra has has trouble you know
there have been tantric systems in India
that were they emphas exercise sexual
practices and things like that. In fact,
uh I went to India one time parasi and I
was staying in a I was be kind of B&B
and the lady came one morning and she
said you have to leave you know and I'm
like why and she said you practice
tantra and I said yeah but it's it's
very very beautiful. It's it's like I
don't know super psychology or something
and very nice and and she said no no
it's very bad and she she made me leave
you know and this is it so even in the
country where it began
uh tantra has a bad name and the word in
the west it has a bad
name so which is strange because it's a
beautiful beautiful clean it's based on
morality it's based on
good behavior and uh so anyway uh the
course that ACI designed for d we call
diamond way because we don't want to use
the word tundra the course that we
designed for diamond way is is I believe
it's the best ever done in history and
it covers all of the topics of diamond
way and it's a tough
course this morning I saw an old
survivor of uh Kendra. Where is she?
Yeah, she's an old survivor of the
original tentry course which was seven
years. Those guys suffered for seven
years and the homeworks are like 200
questions or three people finished the
homeworks. uh and uh so anyway it's a
wonderful wonderful course uh but uh I
think there's another secular again
there's a division of secular practice
of diamond way and I use this picture uh
because tantra the nickname for tantra
in tundra is vajayana which means
diamond
way but
also I think there could be a secular
diamond way where you take the
attitudes of those teachings and not the
Buddhism and you use it. And my example
to you would be 19 years in a corporate,
you know, skyscraper in Manhattan. Uh,
practicing Diamond Ray secretly. And no
one in the company knows. Uh, you're no
one knows you're even a Buddhist. Uh,
you know, and by the way, a lot of my
staff was Asian. You know, I hired a lot
of people through Chinatown. uh refugee
project. I I hired a lot of refugees
from Asia, from many countries and uh so
I never told anybody that I was and but
I used it all the time and
people responded to it and and this
whole attitude diamond way attitude that
the world is special, something special,
something beautiful.
I think there could be a secular
uh application and uh and I I've I did
it and it works and and we became the
largest company of our kind in the
world and I think a lot of it was
because of Diamond Way attitudes
uh spreading in the company
like COVID COVID diamond way uh okay And
I think maybe the cutest kind of diamond
way is where it spreads to you and you
don't know it spread to you. That's real
secret
practice. You're doing diamond way and
you don't know you're doing diamond way.
So anyway,
uh those are the five houses that I'm
thinking about. I'm gonna uh stop there.
Okay. And uh what I'd like to do today
is lead a meditation. We got about half
an hour. Uh and I'd like to lead a short
meditation. Uh and we're going to
meditate about the five houses.
Okay. So get comfortable.
uh for me uh so I do this every morning
and and I think
uh I think the most important thing is
to get comfortable so you don't have to
move especially when you're in a group.
Okay, when you're in a group it's an
extra
responsibility not to bother the other
people. Also, when you're in a group,
somebody's going to cough right next to
you. And you have to be compassionate.
And you can't get angry during your
meditation about the noisy person next
to you. Everyone always sits next to the
noisiest person. I'm telling you, I
don't know how that's possible, but it
it does. Okay? So, don't worry about
me. My main thing you know quick
meditation
posture is uh
obviously trying to get to a position
where you're not going to
move and then uh shoulders back slightly
tummy dunk in
slightly lower belly
slightly pushed in but don't go crazy
okay don't go crazy slightly
And that will help you. Don't overdo
it. And then you
can I've had retreats, long retreats
where I kept my eyes slightly open and
look
down without lowering your chin. So chin
is still
straight. Uh but the eyes are down. And
that's an option. If you get sleepy, I I
think the extra light works like that.
Okay? If you can, then close your
eyes. If you can, if you want to go
further, focus
here. So, by the way, don't go like
this. Some people are
like, you know, don't don't hurt your
eyes. Okay? You're focusing your
attention here, but not your eyes. Okay?
Although you can slightly raise your
eyes. It helps.
And then we're going to your hands just
should be
comfortable. And I, you know, left hand
down first, right hand down first. After
meditating for nearly 50 years, it
doesn't matter. And make sure your hands
are relaxed.
That's we're going to count a certain
number of breaths and then I'll I'll
stop you and uh we'll go on to the next
part.
Okay. Out breath first, in breath
second.
Please think of someone that you really
admire and think about the good
qualities they have. Especially
someone who has a good quality that you
would like to develop. Maybe you don't
have that quality
or you don't have that quality as much
as they
do and they really have it. And then
think about them. Bring a specific
person to mind. They don't have to be a
Buddhist. Just
choose certain quality. There are other
qualities may not
be that amazing. But this one colony
they have is really
amazing and it's something I would like
to have. The quality I would like to
have.
Think about times you've watched them
and they have displayed
And secondly, imagine that you are
honoring them for this quality. I would
imagine that you
are mentioned to them how much you
admire this
quality and you could give them a small
gift or
something. Mainly you express to them
how much you admire this quote. So
imagine that you could talk to
them. Imagine they could hear in their
mind what you are saying.
Now try next step. Try to think
of something you did in the last few
days which was not very
nice. Maybe you criticized somebody.
Maybe
you say on someone's
faults. Try to
isolate. Try to pick out
one negative thing you've done in the
last few days. And of course, we've done
many, but try to think of
one that's kind of your usual problem.
Think about
it. Express regret for
it to the universe. I'm sorry I I did
that again.
I'll work on. By the way, if you
keep apologizing for the same mistake
over and over and
over, at some point you will
change. So don't think it's hopeless. If
you don't
apologize, then you could go on forever
doing that. But if you make it a daily
practice before your meditation to
apologize to the universe for this bad
habit you have then it it
will build up strength and you will be
able to break that but it may take
time. So we have to do it daily.
And now put equal effort into thinking
about
something, some good habit you have,
something good that you do
frequently, some
attitude, some action
or some way of speaking
that is habitual for you and it's
It's
good. Rejoice. Be
happy. I imagine I'm still telling the
same
person that I was admiring. So I will
imagine they're sitting with me and I'll
say, "Hey, I may have bad habits, but I
have this I have this one good habit.
I imagine I'm telling them about it.
Rejoice. A lot of people have trouble
rejoicing. So don't blow it up.
Don't Don't not take it
seriously. Try to become an expert in
rejoicing.
and ask for teachings
today. Pray
that the world teaches you something new
today. I think as you get older, when
you get to my age, you think you don't
have much left to learn.
If you're open-minded and you
are watching the world to learn new
things and you you get in the
habit of learning new
things, the world will teach you, things
will come and they are amazing. Each
year of your
life, you
learn wonderful new things.
So make a request to the universe.
Please teach me something cool that I
know.
You know all of us are fortunate. I
think most of us have
teachers. And even if we don't have
formal teachers, we have good people in
our
life. Could be a spouse, could be
children, could be friends. But they are
nice people. They are good people.
They're a good
example. Ask those people to stay in
your
life. Ask them to help you be a good
person.
And I'd like to think uh I'd like to ask
you to think
about whether or not Classics's
house is the house that attracts
you. And today in this
meditation, we're going to go to each
house and
imagine that I am a master of this
house. So whether or not you're
attracted to classic
house, maybe especially if you're not
attracted to classics
house, try to imagine
yourself a real
master of the classics. And it's a
vast a vast vast subject
of
beautiful information basically
spiritual information. So you
just imagine whether you're attracted to
it or
not. Imagine you are a true master of
the classics.
This is your house. Maybe you are
even helping to direct the
house. You are a master of the
classics and you are helping to direct
this house.
It's your responsibility
to share the
classes both with people who are
interested
spiritually and with people who are not
spiritually. It's kind of your job to
find strategies
to share the beautiful ideas of the
classics to both spiritual
people and to people who are not
interested in in
spirituality. Imagine that's your
responsibility as the master of
classical
Now switch
houses. You are a master of somati
house. What does it feel like to be a a
real master
meditator? What do you imagine it feels
like?
And how will you use this med meditation
skill to help both spiritual
seekers and normal people who are maybe
not interested in
in spirituality?
as a meditation master, as a sami
master. Can you imagine like almost
designing programs
for for both populations, both different
kinds of people?
Okay, let's move on to mountain house.
Now
you're master of mountain house. You may
be a classics master
also. You may be a samati master also.
But I'd like you
to drop those two and focus on being
a master means you are a retreat
master. You're very very
experienced. You're very very
passionate and you're very very good at
doing retreat. You're very well
trained and
just really
enjoyed being a retreat
master. Whether or not that's true,
pretend pretend you're retreat
master. How does it feel?
and drop the identification and switch
to a staircase house master. I'm a mun
master. I have
mastered
many meditations and
practices of the steps of the path.
I know that 14 years of stuff very
well and I have an
experiential awareness of all those
steps. I I meditated on those steps. I
practiced those steps. They're part of
me. It's part of who I
am. I'm a real master staircase.
How would you use that for
spiritual seekers to help spiritual
seekers and how would you use that in
the normal
world in traditional spirituality?
Okay, switch hats. In in the ancient
language, it means switch houses. Now
you're a diamond cross master.
You are one of
the greatest, most experienced, most
wise, most
well-trained masters of
diamonds, master teacher of the
diamond. And again, you're thinking
How can this house help people who are
interested in traditional
spirituality? And how can this house
also
serve people who are not interested in
that? And by the way, of course, people
can switch and it it happens. People
think they're not interested in
spirituality and then after a year or
two they suddenly become attracted to
the spiritual side. There are people who
switch but generally as a diamond house
master it's your responsibility
to take care of both groups.
We did a meditation on the five
houses. We pretended that we were a
master even of the houses that were
maybe not so interested
in. And we thought about ways that we
could serve people who are interested in
in a traditional spiritual
path and then other people who are not
interested in in that. But we thought
about as a master of each house, we
thought about ways to serve both
populations.
Now let's dedicate that good karma.
I like to imagine light coming out of my
body like
sunlight, like bursting out like
sunlight
and you know gradually spreading
across the place where I live and
spreading to other
places. It may not be a visible
sunlight. Maybe it's just intentional
sunlight
and as it touches the planet as it moves
across the
planet people are inspired and people
feel
happier
because I have dedicated the good karma
this meditation
to in the sunlight.
Okay, you can open your eyes.
Uh, there's a bathroom problem in two
ways. I think there's some kind of
backup of somebody must have done a big
one. And don't forget there are outouses
here, but
uh in the parking lot. And I went,
they're pretty nice. I mean, they're
okay.
Uh, one more picture.
Uh, they're
fixed. All right. Next picture,
Francisco. I think it's This is Galce's
cabin, you know. And when
I when I try, this is the one I stay in.
You don't get to see it. Uh, but, uh,
the vibe is is wonderful, you know. Her
vibe is is there. I I often stay there.
And uh to me when I talk to people about
Diamond Mountain
uh this is what I show them, you know,
and if I was going to sell what do you
call mountain house, you know, if I was
going to sell mountain house, I would
say here's mountain house, you know,
here's the what
side? The spiritual side. Okay. Here's
the spiritual side of of
of Mountain House. You know, this is
the retreat side of Mount This is sorry,
this is the spiritual Buddhist side of
Mountain House. Now, what's the secular
side look like? Next
picture. Okay. And uh this is an actual
program that was held
here about three four week three weeks
ago. four weeks ago I came down this is
a new
organization started in Asia it's called
innovation
retreats they special Stanley Chen uh
founded
it assist him on it uh and then uh they
had a wonderful group uh flew in from
many countries and
uh and they held this uh they held this
and and by the This is this
temple. This picture is this temple.
Okay. And I walked in the the door, you
know. And I I opened the door and I was
like,
"Wow." You know, and I was
like for how many years? 20 years. I
wanted to have business retreats here,
corporate retreats. We used to have them
in my business. Terrible things.
Uh, but I walked in and I saw I saw this
setup, you know, and I was
like, damn, I've been waiting for 20
years for this, you know. And this is
the secular
side of uh what do they call that
house? Yeah. Mountain house, you know.
And I was God uh I was talking to Sunum.
She said her jaw dropped and my jaw
dropped. And I was like, yeah, this is
what I had vision. You know, this is the
secular side, the non-spiritual side of
retreat.
And and I I did those retreats in my
business.
And and I had many many uh I don't know
how to
say revolutionary
uh ideas about business processes and
business products. And uh all was
invented in a retreat like this. Okay.
All was created in a retreat like that,
you know, which is going to save a whole
culture that would otherwise disappear
in this world. And uh so it's a I think
it's incredible. I think it's amazing.
Now the problem is it's
expensive to set up the place like that.
There's two problems. Number one, three
problems.
Everywhere you see this cute little
coloration thing on the walls, that's a
leak. And we built this place by hand.
You know, I was there, Ben was there,
Kendra was there, the other guy wasn't
here yet. Uh, and uh, boy, we So anyway,
it leaks. We We didn't know what we were
doing. And we actually blocked off the
electrical outlets because it's
dangerous. The water gets into
electricity. And so that's kind of
preventing us from having
uh from making this into like a
corporate retreat place where you could
come to do corporate retreat. We're not
going to we're not going to throw out
all the Buddhists. We're just going to
have different weekends or different
weeks. You know, we'd like to serve both
communities. Every house should serve
both communities. So anyway, we'd like
to set it up like that. This company had
a lot of money. They came in, they set
it up. Unfortunately, they took it
home. Okay. So, you understand what I'm
setting you up for? Uh, we would like to
uh buy the necessary equipment and and
backdrops and things to do corporate
things here. And I think it would be
very popular and it would help support
Diamond Mountain and we could influence
the whole world. I think it's a very
wonderful possibility. Okay. And then we
have to pay people to do that. We have
to train ACI teachers to do that. So
anyway, we need money. I do a fundraiser
every retreat. This is my fundraiser. I
have exactly 30 seconds.
And I like to put guilt pressure. This
is something my mom taught
me. My parents split up, you know, and
my mom's like, "Oh, your dad's a good
man. Sometimes he does send the alimony,
you know. Sometimes he does send us
money." Meaning he doesn't usually. And
she guilt trip. He would guilt. It's
called guilt trip in English. So I'm
going to guilt trip you. Uh, grandpa has
raised
$23,500. Okay.
$3,500 was donated to me by the Russian
uh students here and I'd like to thank
them and uh they asked me to use it for
any charitable project that I wanted to.
So I'd like to use it for the
corporatization of this retreat
center and um 20,000 is comes from the
hard work of SI around and myself
uh at at DCI and SEU. So we give 12% of
our gross profit every year. So we would
like to throw in
23,500. My wife and I will throw in
another 1500. So, we'll make it
25,000 for this project. And it involves
uh DCI and uh sorry, it involves Diamond
Mountain and
ACI. So, I call it Firehouse World,
meaning we can reach out to the general
world, the real world. And if you'd like
to contribute, there's the there's the
By the way, you don't have to give
$1,000. If you if you give $10, you get
your finger in the pie. My teacher used
to say, "Get your finger in the pie.
Give $5, give $1." Doesn't matter. Get
your finger in the karma pie. And uh
it's okay. If you're a fat cat,
Pango, if if you can give 10,000, that's
wonderful. If you cannot, then give give
$50 or something like that. Okay. So it
goes to uh training the necessary ACI
staff uh buying the actual equipment and
then uh setting it up here.
When we when we do secular house stuff,